Guide to the Hendrik Willem van Loon papers, 1884-1972.
Van Loon, Hendrick Willem papers,
- Series IV. Manuscript material
  - Subseries IVb. Articles
    - "On Contemplating the Coining of the Coming Revolution From the Front Porch of the Players," n.d. (Box 25, Folder 76)
    - "The Kitchen of Charlemagne and of Henry VIII," n.d. (Box 25, Folder 77)
    - "In the Matter of One-Carl Van Doren," n.d. (Box 25, Folder 78)
    - "Words Fail Me," n.d. (Box 25, Folder 79)
  - Broadcasts, Lectures and Serials
    - "Van Loon's Geography" ;Sept. 21, 1932 (Box 25, Folder 80)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 6, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 81)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 10, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 81)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 13, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 82)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 17, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 82)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 20, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 83)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 24, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 83)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 27, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 84)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Oct. 31, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 84)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 3, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 85)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 5, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 85)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 7, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 85)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 10, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 86)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 14, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 86)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 17, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 87)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 24, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 88)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Nov. 28, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 88)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Dec. 1, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 89)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Dec. 8, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 90)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Dec. 12, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 90)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Dec. 15, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 91)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Dec. 19, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 91)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Feb. 19, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 92)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Feb. 26, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 93)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Mar. 5, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 94)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Mar. 12, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 95)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Mar. 19, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 96)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Mar. 26, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 97)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Apr. 2, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 98)
    - "Day of Glory" ;Apr. 2, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 99)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Apr. 9, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 100)
    - "Van Loon's interpretation of Crown Prince Gustav Adolf of Sweden" ;Apr. 9, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 101)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Apr. 16, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 102)
    - NBC Broadcast ;Apr. 23, 1939 (Box 25, Folder 103)
    - "Let us turn our lumber-yards into bonfires" ;Nov. 11, 1942 (Box 25, Folder 104)
    - "Freedom House" ;Dec. 24, 1942 (Box 25, Folder 105)
    - "The Laughing Cavalier" ;Dec. 13, 1943 (Box 25, Folder 106)
    - "Words at War-The 9th Commandment" ;Dec. 28, 1943 (Box 25, Folder 107)
    - "From The JV Vandercock Broadcast" ;Mar. 11, 1944 (Box 25, Folder 108)
    - "The Challenge" ;n. d. (Box 25, Folder 109)
    - "Near Antwerp (NBC)" ;n.d. (Box 25, Folder 110)
    - "Rubber" ;n.d. (Box 25, Folder 111)
    - "The Laughing Philosopher" ;n. d. (Box 25, Folder 112)
    - "The Congress of Vienna" ;carbon, 17 pages (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - "The History of Man" ;carbon, list of lectures (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - "Lecture Announcements" ;3 pamphlets (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - "Cunard Cruise Line Lectures" ;handwritten draft, 7 pages (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - "Cunard Cruise Line Lectures" ;handwritten draft, 39 pages (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - "Cunard Cruise Line Lectures" ;handwritten draft p. 1-30 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - "Cunard Cruise Line Lectures" ;p. 31-58 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - "History of the Dutch Navy" ;carbon (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - "Modern European History" ;miscellaneous typescript pages (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - "Modern European History" ;typescript p. 1-20 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - "Modern European History" ;p. 21-40 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - "Modern European History" ;p. 41-57 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - "Modern European History" ;p. 58-81 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - "Modern European History" ;p. 82-106 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - "The French Revolution" ;carbon, general bibliography (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - "The French Revolution" ;p. 1-19 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - "The French Revolution" ;p. 20-54 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;handwritten draft p. 1-35 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;p. 36-70 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;p. 71-101 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;annotated typescript p. 1-30 (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;p. 31-56 (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;carbon p. 1-30 (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - "The Ten Commandments" ;p. 31-60 (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - "The Week in America" ;miscellaneous handwritten and carbon pages (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - "With a Dutch Accent" ;miscellaneous handwritten and carbon pages (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - "Kipling Was Right" ;The New Mason Dixon Line carbon p. 1-14 (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - "Kipling Was Right II" ;miscellaneous handwritten and carbon pages (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - "The Spectator" ;miscellaneous handwritten and carbon pages (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - "Common Sense and the Alphabet" ;carbon, 6 pages (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - "Hijackers' Sea" ;annotated typescript 8 pages (Box 26, Folder 31)
    - "The Canal That Goes A-Climbing" ;annotated typescript 7 pages (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - "Traveling With Your Head" ;annotated handwritten draft carbon Aug. 18, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - "Traveling With A Hobby" ;carbon 16 pages (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - "USA-An Empire in Spite of Itself" ;annotated handwritten, typescript and carbon (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - "Junior Book of Authors" ;carbon, 8 pages, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - "The General Idea for a Revue Done in a New Way" ;carbon (Box 26, Folder 37)
    - "The Tower Talks" (Box 26, Folder 37)
    - "The Stories I Liked as a Child as Retold to my Grandchildren" ;typescript forward and dedication] (Box 26, Folder 38)
    - "The Story of a Homesick Boy" ;typescript, 16 pages (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - "The Story of a Homesick Boy" ;handwritten draft (Box 26, Folder 40)
    - "A Chronicle of Freedom" ;annotated typescript (Box 26, Folder 41)
    - "The Story of the Old Netherlands" ;typescript, 7 pages (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - "The Tower Talks continued" (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - "The Hidden Door" ;miscellaneous typescript pages (Box 26, Folder 43)
    - "Janker Jan" ;handwritten draft, Chapter 1 (Box 26, Folder 44)
    - "In the Palace of the Governor" ;handwritten draft, carbon Chapter 1 (Box 26, Folder 45)
    - "An Innocent Man is Done to the Death" ;Chapter 2 (Box 26, Folder 46)
    - "Picture of a Roman Gentleman and a Few of His Contemporaries" ;Chapter 3 (Box 26, Folder 47)
    - "Eleanor?" ;handwritten draft Chapter 4 (Box 26, Folder 48)
    - "Janker Jan" ;typescript copy (Box 26, Folder 49)
    - "N/A" ;carbon forward (Box 26, Folder 50)
    - "The Laughing Cavalier" ;miscellaneous handwritten, typescript and carbon pages (Box 26, Folder 51)
    - "The Laughing Cavalier" ;typescript Chapter 1 (Box 26, Folder 52)
    - "George VI" ;annotated handwritten draft and carbon (Box 26, Folder 53)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 1 (Box 26, Folder 53)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 2 (Box 26, Folder 54)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 3 (Box 26, Folder 55)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 4 (Box 26, Folder 56)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 5 (Box 26, Folder 57)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 6 (Box 26, Folder 58)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 7 (Box 26, Folder 59)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 8 (Box 26, Folder 60)
    - "George VI" ;Chapter 9 (Box 26, Folder 61)
    - "George VI" ;annotated handwritten draft and carbon Chapter 10 (Box 26, Folder 62)
    - "Edward VIII" ;carbon Installments 1-10 (Box 26, Folder 63)
    - "Napoleon and Josephine" ;miscellaneous handwritten and carbon pages (Box 26, Folder 64-66)
    - "King Features" ;typescript and carbon p. 1-16 (Box 26, Folder 67)
    - "King Features" ;p. 17-28 (Box 26, Folder 68)
    - "King Features" ;handwritten and typescript p. 29-32 (Box 26, Folder 69)
    - "King Features" ;p. 33-38 (Box 26, Folder 70)
    - "King Features" ;p. 39-46 (Box 26, Folder 71)
    - "King Features" ;p. 47-52 (Box 26, Folder 72)
    - "King Features" ;p. 53-59 (Box 26, Folder 73)
    - "King Features" ;p. 60-70 (Box 26, Folder 74)
    - "King Features" ;p. 71-78 (Box 26, Folder 75)
    - "King Features" ;p. 79-84 (Box 26, Folder 76)
    - "King Features" ;p. 85-92 (Box 26, Folder 77)
    - "King Features" ;p. 93-97 (Box 26, Folder 78)
    - "King Features" ;p. 98-109 (Box 26, Folder 79)
    - "King Features" ;p. 110-123 (Box 26, Folder 80)
    - "King Features" ;p. 124-130 (Box 26, Folder 81)
    - "King Features" ;p. 131-138 (Box 26, Folder 82)
    - "The English War" ;Annotated typescript of Hendrik Willem van Loon's thesis written in German (Box 26, Folder 83)
    - "The English War" ;Intr. 15-30 (Box 26, Folder 83)
    - "The English War" ;p. 1-34 (Box 26, Folder 84)
    - "The English War" ;Intr. 31-44 (Box 26, Folder 85)
    - "The English War" ;W. 1-25 (Box 26, Folder 86)
    - "The English War" ;A. 1-21 (Box 26, Folder 87)
    - "The English War" ;p. 1-7 (Box 26, Folder 88)
    - "The English War" ;p. 8-25 (Box 26, Folder 89)
    - "The English War" ;p. 26-52 (Box 26, Folder 90)
    - "The English War" ;p. 53-63 (Box 26, Folder 91)
    - "The English War" ;p. 64-76 (Box 26, Folder 92)
    - "The English War" ;p. 77-85 Belgien 1-10 (Box 26, Folder 93)
    - "The English War" ;p. 181-191 (Box 26, Folder 94)
    - "The English War" ;bp. 61-107 (Box 26, Folder 95)
    - "The English War" ;bp. 108-140 (Box 26, Folder 96)
    - "The English War" ;p. 141-180 (Box 26, Folder 97)
    - "The English War" ;B. 1-6 Wv. 1-17 Ar. 1-34 (Box 26, Folder 98)
    - "The English War" ;Ar. 35-49 (Box 26, Folder 99)
    - "The English War" ;bp. 1-25 (Box 26, Folder 100)
    - "The English War" ;bp. 26-60 (Box 26, Folder 101)
- Series V. Printed material
  Printed material consists mainly of English and foreign translations of various van Loon books: articles about van Loon in both foreign and American papers and magazines; reviews; promotional book material; cruise ship pamphlets; copies of illustrations that appeared in various newspapers and magazines; and miscellaneous clippings.
  - Subseries Va. Printed material, mostly photocopied
    - Articles about Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 27, Folder 1-4)
    - Articles, divorce (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Articles, foreign (Box 27, Folder 6-8)
    - The Arts (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Fall of the Dutch Republic (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Van Loon's Geography (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Van Loon's Lives (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Report to St. Peter (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Story of Mankind/Thomas Jefferson (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Book reviews; miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 15-16)
    - Commercial views (of Cambridge) (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Cunard Cruise Line material ( Hendrik Willem van Loon lecturer) 1934 Jan. -May (Box 27, Folder 18-19)
    - Obituary material (several photocopied clippings, news accounts, bulletins) (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Publisher's promotional material (Box 27, Folder 21-22)
    - One copy Netherlands News; Vol. 9, No. 1; March 15, 1944 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Two copies De Varende Hollander; Deel V, No. 6; March 15, 194 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - One copy Netherlands News Digest; Vol. 11, No. 13; March 27, 1944 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Two copies The Spectator; No. 4, 445; September 6, 1913 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Reviews/clippings (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Reviews/clippings "Invasion" (Box 28, Folder 2-3)
    - Reviews/clippings "The Story of the Pacific" (Box 28, Folder 4-5)
    - Foreign articles (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Articles about Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Articles written by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Illustrations by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Copies of illustrations by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Copies of cartoons from The Nation by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Copies of sketches by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper photos of Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Menus from dinners attended by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Cunard Cruise material (Box 28, Folder 15-16)
    - Obituary materials (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 18-20)
  - Subseries Vb. Magazines containing Hendrik Willem van Loon articles, reviews and related magazines
    - The Atlantic; Feb. 1942 (Box 29)
    - Century; 1917 issue, 1916, 1915 (Box 29)
    - National Geographic; June 1916 (Box 29)
    - Knickerbocker Weekly; 1944: #'s 4, 5, 18, 20; 1942 Vol. 2 # 30 (Box 29)
    - The New Yorker; March 20, 27th, April 3rh 1943 (Box 29)
    - The Nation; 1921, 1922, 1924 (2 issues), 1944 (Box 29)
    - The Survey; 1924 (Box 29)
    - Survey Graphic; April 1944 (Box 29)
    - Tomorrow; 1942 (2 issues) (Box 29)
    - Ons Zeewezen; Jan. 1929 (Box 29)
    - The Players 13th Annual Revival; 1935 (Box 29)
    - The Seven Seas (Chas. T. Stork and Co.);3 copies (Box 29)
    - Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine; Oct. 1913 (Box 29)
  - Subseries Vc. Books
    - Foreign language translations of various Van Loon books (Box 30-33)
    - Books written by Van Loon: (Box 34)
    - The Arts of Mankind The Home of Mankind The Story of Mankind The Liberation of Mankind Jefferson and Bolivar The Story of the Pacific; Some Books Removed June 1996 see catalog (Box 34)
    - This Changing World written by Samuel S. Fels illustrated by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 34)
- Series VI. Illustrative material
  Illustrative material includes the illustrations made for many van Loon books arranged by book title; sketches for unfinished books; sketchbooks; illustrated stories and unpublished material; illustrated folders, envelopes, and menus; small pen-and-ink and watercolor sketches either mounted or on mats; ornate matted sketches; book jackets; many miscellaneous sketches; and portraits of van Loon by other artists.
  - Subseries VIa. Illustrations Made For Van Loon Books
    - Adriaen Block (Box 40)
    - America (Box 40)
    - America (Box 75-76)
    - Ancient Man (Box 38)
    - Around the World with the Alphabet (Box 36)
    - Around the World with the Alphabet (Box 78-79)
    - The Arts of Mankind (Box 39-40)
    - The Arts of Mankind (Box 76-77)
    - The Average Man (Box 40)
    - Christmas Carols (Box 36)
    - Christmas Carols (Box 79-80)
    - Dutch History (Box 39)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree (Mapcase-folder 13)
    - Geography (Box 41)
    - Geography (Box 41A, Folder 11-46)
    - Geography (Box 41B, Folder 1-10)
    - Gulliver's Travels (Box 37)
    - Jean Navarrin (Box 41C)
    - Scandinavia (Box 41C, Folder 1-10)
    - Scandinavia (Box 41D, Folder 11-20)
    - Ships (Box 37)
    - A Short History of Music (Box 41D)
    - The Songs America Sings (Box 41B, Folder 16-22)
    - The Songs America Sings (Box 41E, Folder 1-15)
    - The Songs We Sing (Box 36)
    - The Songs We Sing (Box 81)
    - The Story of Mankind (Box 38)
    - Tolerance (Box 37)
    - Wilbur the Hat (Box 35-36)
    - Wilbur the Hat (Box 82-83)
    - Sketches for unfinished books (Box 42)
    - Miscellaneous sketches (Box 42)
    - Sketches for a child's book (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Simon and Schuster sketches (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Dodd, Mead and Co. sketches (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Drawings used in "The Story of Hendrik Willem van Loon" (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Material entitled "The original concept of 'A Short History of Discovery'" (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Untitled published drawings (Box 44)
    - 1 hardcover notebook of sketches for various books (Box 44)
    - Sketches for various books (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous sketches (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous colored sketches on illustrator's board (Box 83-84)
    - Miscellaneous sketches of buildings, maps, and various scenes (Box 84-86)
    - Small envelopes of miscellaneous original sketches (Box 45)
    - Illustrated story for Rene Scudamore (Box 45)
    - 5 sketchbooks (Box 46)
    - 1 guest book with illustrations by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 46)
    - 1 illustrated story about the French Revolution in a notebook dated 1905 (Box 46)
    - 14 sketchbooks (Box 47)
    - Illustrated folders (Box 48)
    - Illustrated envelopes (Box 48)
    - 6 etching impressions (Box 49)
    - 5 menu sketches (Box 49)
    - 1 envelope of small mounted sketches in watercolor and pen and ink (Box 49)
    - 2 folders of miscellaneous matted sketches (Box 49)
    - 17 pages from Woman's Home Companion with Van Loon article and illustrations (Box 49)
    - Book covers from various Van Loon books (Box 49)
    - Copies of Van Loon illustrations in various magazines (Box 49)
    - Portraits of Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 50)
    - Several unsigned (Box 50)
    - 1 by: Theodore Bolton (Box 50)
    - Oversized prints (Box 87)
    - Bettina Steince (Box 87)
    - Oyvind Sorensen (Box 50)
    - R. Taylor, 1939 (Box 50)
    - Ruth Hoffman (Box 50)
    - Muncher (?) 1909 (?) (Box 50)
    - Karolin (?) Nenplatz, March 1909 (Box 50)
    - 2 pages of monogram sketches, July 5, 1910 (Box 50)
    - 1 oversized duplicate photo (Box 50)
    - 1 sketch initialled by H.V.D.V.L. (Box 50)
    - 1 folder of miscellaneous sketches (Van Loon's Lives ?) (Box 50)
    - Several oversized and reprinted sketches (Box 50)
    - Miscellaneous sketches of maps and painted scenes (Box 68)
    - 18 watercolor sketches on heavy cardboard (Mapcase-folder 1-9)
    - Watercolor sketch of Elephant Up a Tree on heavy cardboard (Mapcase-folder 13)
    - Black and white watercolor sketch of storm (Mapcase-folder 13)
    - Original watercolor sketches, alphabet theme (Mapcase-folder 10-12)
    - 2 sketches with Nazi theme (on thick sketch paper) (Box 89, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous sketch, blue landscape (Box 89, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous sketch (on thick sketch paper) (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - 2 watercolor sketches on heavy cardboard of cat, dog and lion (Box 89, Folder 2)
    - Dutch advertisement with illustration by Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - Bookmark for The Arts (Mapcase-folder 17)
    - Back of book jacket for The Arts (Mapcase-folder 17)
    - Map to locate and date the most important events in the history of the arts, 1937 (Mapcase-folder 17)
    - Map of Europe (Mapcase-folder 16)
    - Map of the United States, 1935 (Mapcase-folder 16)
    - Illustrations from NY Tribune, Dec. 1,8, 15, 1918 (Mapcase-folder 16)
    - Large canvas portrait of Hendrik Willem van Loon, Frame 1
    - 17 reproductions of various scenes (Box 88)
    - Photo of Hendrik Willem van Loon's hands (Box 89, Folder 4)
    - Sketch of hands (Box 89, Folder 5)
    - Sketch of Erasmus (Box 89, Folder 6)
    - Photo of Hendrik Willem van Loon with statue of Erasmus (Mapcase-folder 14)
    - "Water and Sky" (1935) - ink/watercolor on watercolor paper (Box 89, Folder 1)
- Series VII. Memorabilia
  Memorabilia is divided into two subseries: Subseries a. Includes scrapbooks, guest books, photograph albums and photographs, notebooks, diaries, passports, pamphlets, certificates, diplomas, phonograph records, games, puzzles, and miscellaneous. Subseries b. Collected memorabilia includes various miscellaneous documents, volumes, and reprints collected by van Loon.
  - Subseries VIIa. Scrapbooks, guest books, photograph albums and photographs, notebooks, diaries, passports, pamphlets, certificates, diplomas, phonograph records, games, puzzles, and miscellaneous.
    - Scrapbook, news clippings of articles written by Hendrik Willem van Loon, especially a column, "Deliberate Reflections." c. 1939-1940 (Box 53)
    - Scrapbook, news clippings from various papers, reviews ca.1937; also includes certificate from Finnish Relief Fund Inc. 1939-1940, Herbert Hoover signed. (Box 53)
    - Photograph album, views of Switzerland, Washington, Niagara Falls, and many small family snapshots. (Box 53)
    - Guest book, 1920-1938 see separate listing next page) (Box 54)
    - Volume, blank pages of The Story of Mankind, contains press clippings and reviews of the book (Box 54)
    - Two record notebooks (in German or Dutch) dated Dec. 28, 1938, with very few entries (Box 54)
    - Diary, begins Nov. 30, 1907, intermittent entries through April 1, 1909 (Box 54)
    - Diary, intermittent dates 1913 and 1914, contains original sketches, clippings photos, etc. (Box 54)
    - Passports and pamphlets (Box 55)
    - Games and puzzles
    - Van Loon's Geography Picture Puzzle (Box 34)
    - Jigsaw puzzle of Mungo and Noodles (Hendrik Willem van Loon's dogs) (Box 34)
    - Van Loon's Story of Mankind Game (Box 34)
    - Hendrik Van Loon's Wide World Game (Box 60)
    - Guest book volume 1920-1924 (Box 54)
      Guests:
      Dwight Franklin, artist
      Paul V. Kellogg, editor, Presidential Committee on Economic Security, 1934-1935
      Lewis Browne, writer
      Van Wyck Brooks, The Seven Arts
      Margaret Bowditch, relative through Eliza
      Oscar Howard, illustrator for New York World
      Lila Howard, sculptress
      George Hand Wright, artist, Dutch Treat club member
      Jay Norwood Darling, (J.N. Ding) cartoonist
      Hugh Lofting, author Dr. Doolittle
      Richard Connell, author Murder at Sea
    - Guest book volume 1925 (Box 54)
      Harry Hansen, editor, war correspondence
      Frank Case, Algonquin Hotel
      Bayard Veiller, playwright
      Everett Shinn, artist
      Grace Miller White, author Tess of the Storm Country
    - Guest book volume 1926 (Box 54)
      Theodore Dreiser, author An American Tragedy
    - Guest book volume 1931 (Box 54)
      Frank Lloyd Wright, architect
      Victor Hammer, (Trygue)
    - Guest book volume 1935 (Box 54)
      Thomas and Katia Mann, philosopher
    - Guest book volume 1937 (Box 54)
      H.G. Wells, author
    - Guest book volume 1938 (Box 54)
      Julian LaRose Harris, editor, Pulitzer Prize, Nation's roil of honor
    - World War I (Box 56, Folder 1-3)
    - Certificates, diplomas and documents (Box 56, Folder 4-6)
    - Genealogy (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon and EBVL engagement (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 56, Folder 9-10)
    - Two envelopes addressed to Hendrik Willem van Loon (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Photographs, duplicates and negatives (Box 57)
    - Publicity pictures for movie version of The Story of Mankind by Warner Brothers, released in 1957, directed by Irwin Alien (a Cambridge Production in Technicolor) see list of actors and actresses: (Box 57)
    - Vincent Price, Ronald Colman, group photos (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - John Carradine, group photos, Nick Cravat, Vincent Price, Ronald Colman (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Vincent Price, Ronald Colman, Groucho Marx, Harry Ruby, Harpo Marx, Chico Marx, Anthony Dexter, Melinda Marx, Frank Rapport (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Hedy Lamar (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Mayo, Helmut Dantine, Peter Lorre (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - Dennis Hopper, Marie Windsor, Francis X. Bushman, Charles Coburn (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - Reginald Gardiner, Frank Pangborn, Marie Wilson, Austin Green, Cesar Romero, Toni Gerrie or Cathy O'Donnell, Marvin Miller, George E. Stone, Edward Everett Horton (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - Dani Crayne, Cedric Hardwicke, Bobby Watson, Jim (Don) Ameche, Reginald Sheffield, and several unidentified people (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon snapshots, c. 1902-c. 1944 (dated) with Edward Filene and Marguerite Davis, 1932 with Grace Castagnatta and Ruby Fuhr, 1938 Cornell dorm room c. 1902, [4x5] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon snapshots, ca. 1902-1944, [4x5] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon snapshots, ca. 1902-1941, [4x5] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon and "Jimmie" travel photos, [4x5] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 4)